<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
        SYSTEM "http://helpserver.labs.intellij.net/help/html-entities.dtd">
<topic xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://helpserver.labs.intellij.net/help/topic.v2.xsd"
        xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        title="Capitalization"
        id="capitalization">
    <markdown>
        <![CDATA[

##Title

<tip>The current Windows guidelines use sentence capitalization for actions. However, many of Microsoft products still title-capitalize actions according to the previous guidelines. Mac OS X also title-capitalizes actions. Since IntelliJ IDEs are cross-platform, we use title capitalization as well.</tip>

###Use for
* Actions: buttons, menus and links that invoke an action
* Tabs
* Group headers
* Table headers
* Dialog and message box headers


###Rules
* Always capitalize the first and the last words.

* Capitalize the words in-between except:

    * articles: *a, an, the*,
    * coordinating conjunctions: *and, or, but*,
    * prepositions of four and less letters which are not a part of a phrasal verb: *in, with*.

* In hyphenated phrases, capitalize all nouns, adjectives and adverbs: *Auto-Indent, Command-Line Launcher*.
Do not capitalize articles, prepositions and conjunctions: *Side-by-Side, Drag-and-Drop*.


###Examples
*Compare With…*— the short preposition with is capitalized because it is the last word.

*Compare with Latest Repository Version* — with is not capitalized when in the middle.

*Check Out from Version Control* — out is a part of the phrasal verb check out and is capitalized.




##Sentence

###Use for
* Labels for UI controls: text boxes, checkboxes, radio buttons, comboboxes, etc.
* Items in comboboxes, lists, trees and tables
* Explanatory texts: error messages, tooltips/balloons, instructions and status descriptions

###Rules
Capitalize the first word in a sentence, proper nouns and adjectives, and abbreviations.

###Examples
*Control+Shift+F* — keyboard button names are considered proper nouns.

*Accept the terms of the License Agreement* — License Agreement is a proper noun.

*Side-by-side layout* — only the first word of a hyphenated phase is capitalized.




  ]]>
    </markdown>
</topic>